Ernest Klema Papers MS044
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Ernest Klema Papers
1950 -- 1963
1942 -- 2006
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Klema, Ernest D.
MS044
4.8 Linear Feet
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series: Biographical Information; Class Notes from Los Alamos National Laboratory; Class Notes from the University of Illinois; Teaching Notes from the Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology; Subject files and publications from Argonne National Laboratory/Association of Midwest Universities/Northwestern University.
Custodial History
The collection was donated by Dr. Klema. We have contacted Dr. Klema, and he has no more materials to add to the collection.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains class notes from graduate work as well as professional notes and subject files collected by Ernest D. Klema from 1944-1963. Much of the collection contains notes for courses that Klema taught in nuclear engineering and physics at the Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology and the Los Alamos National Laboratory.
Related Materials
Spencer Weart of the American Physical Society and the University of Maryland conducted an interview with Klema as part of interviews of 100 nuclear physicists at Los Alamos.
Biographical / Historical
Ernest Donald Klema was born October 4, 1920 in Wilson, Kansas. He received a B.A. in Chemistry from the University of Kansas in 1941 and an M.A. in Physics from the University of Kansas in 1942. Soon after starting graduate school at Princeton University, his professor and project were transferred to Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory including Klema. There, Klema worked on a Van de Graaff project from 1943-46. According to Klema, the young scientists at Los Alamos organized the Los Alamos University after the war. Courses were organized to permit the scientists to catch up on coursework they had missed during the war. Students traded notes from courses with each other. Instructors for the courses included Enrico Fermi, Victor Weisskopf, Hans Bethe, and Julian Schwinger.
Klema attended the University of Illinois from 1946-1949, working with Al Hanson, Arnold Nordsieck, Jim Allen, and Maurice Goldhaber. From 1949-1950, Klema transferred to Rice University, where he completed his PhD in Physics in 1951 working with Tom Bonner and Gerry Phillips. Klema received a fellowship from the Atomic Energy Commission for his studies at Illinois and Rice. He then worked as a senior physicist at Oak Ridge National Laboratory (ORNL) from 1950-56. While doing research there, Klema also taught two courses (a nuclear physics lecture and an experimental reactor physics laboratory) at the Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology, which trained young nuclear scientists before many universities had set up Nuclear Engineering departments. At ORNL Klema worked with Art Snell and Alvin Weinberg.
Klema was appointed his associate professor of nuclear engineering at the University of Michigan, 1956-58. Moving to Northwestern University, he worked as professor of nuclear and scientific engineering from 1958-68, and as department chair from 1960-67. While at Northwestern, Klema pursued research at the nearby Argonne National Laboratory (ANL). He served as a member of the planning committee for the Associated Midwest Universities (AMU)-Argonne National Laboratory High Voltage Electron Microscope Meeting. AMU was involved in administrating ANL at the time. At Argonne, Klema contributed to the development of an electron microscope and also developed an ANL summer research program for his students from Northwestern.
In 1968, Klema became Dean of the College of Engineering (1968-73) and professor in the College of Engineering (1968-88) at Tufts University. He was also appointed adjunct professor of International Politics at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy from 1973-83, where he researched issues relating to technology and society. As of June, 2006, Klema is Emeritus Professor of Engineering Science and Dean Emeritus of the College of Engineering at Tufts University.
Klema also was a visiting scholar in the Physics Department at Harvard University. He is a fellow of the American Physical Society and the American Nuclear Society. He is a member of the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers, the American Society for Engineering Education, Sigma Xi, Phi Beta Kappa, and Pi Mu Epsilon. He co-founded the company Nuclear Diodes, Inc. Klema's statement on research interests included angular correlations of gamma rays, fission cross sections, empirical nuclear models, semiconductor detectors, and science and technology policy.
Ernest Klema married Virginia Carlock in 1953. They had two children, Donald and Catherine. He died in Bar Harbor, Maine, on October 14, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Klema, Ernest D.; Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology; Faculty papers
- Biographical Information, 1968 -- 2006; MS044.001; 1.2 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains biographical information for Ernest Klema: his CV, publication list, and a 28 page memoir of his career which he wrote in response to a History of Nuclear Physics survey. The memoir contains biographical information and personal accounts and anecdotes of working at Los Alamos National Laboratory, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Northwestern University, and Argonne National Laboratory.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in original order.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Curriculum Vitae and Publication List, Ernest D. Klema, 1968 -- 2006; MS044.001.001.00001 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
  - Memoirs, Ernest D. Klema, Response to History of Nuclear Physics Survey, 1983; MS044.001.001.00002 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
    A letter from Spencer R. Weart, manager of the American Institute of Physics, to Dr. Klema regarding the memoirs was added to this folder from the collection documentation file.
- Class Notes from Los Alamos National Laboratory, 1944 -- 1951; MS044.002; 1.2 Linear Feet
  This series contains class notes from a makeshift Los Alamos University around the time of World War II. Classes were to help young nuclear scientists working at Los Alamos National Laboratory keep up with their studies while away from school. Instructors also included Enrico Fermi, Victor Weisskopf, Hans Bethe, and Julian Schwinger. For each class a different student wrote up notes; class notes were printed and 'traded' among students. The students initially intended to publish the collection of class notes as a textbook in nuclear physics. Each class notebook has been put into a folder.
  - Lecture Series in Nuclear Physics (MDDC 1175), E.M. McMillan et al., United States Atomic Energy Commission, 1947, MS044.002.001.00003 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
  - Hydrodynamics, Unknown Lecturer or Note Taker, 1945; MS044.002.001.00004 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
  - Neutron Physics: A Revision of I. Halpern's Notes on E. Fermi's Lectures, J.G. Beckerly, Atomic Energy Commission, 1945 -- 1951; MS044.002.001.00005 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
  - Neutron Physics: A Course of Lectures by E. Fermi, Notes Transcribed by I. Halpern, 1945 -- 1946; MS044.002.001.00006 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
  - Lectures on Nuclear Physics. Manley, Weisskopf, Schwinger, Zacharias, Feld. Notes by Mac H. Hull, Jr., 1945 -- 1946; MS044.002.001.00007 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
  - Theoretical Mechanics, J. Keller et al., 1945 -- 1946; MS044.002.001.00008 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
  - A Collection of Circuits and Construction Details from the University of Wisconsin - Electrostatic Generators, Compiled by R.D. Krohn, 1945 -- 1946; MS044.002.001.00009 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
  - Electromagnetic Theory: Los Alamos University Lecture Notes, H.A. Bethe and R.E. Marshak, Notes by E.D. Klema, 1945 -- 1946; MS044.002.001.00010 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
  - Electronics/Electro-Magnetic Theory, Unknown Lecturer or Note Taker, 1945 -- 1946; MS044.002.001.00011 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
  - Lecture Series on Nuclear Physics: Fifth Series - The Statistical Theory of Nuclear Reactions, V.F. Weisskopf, 1944 -- 1946; MS044.002.001.00012 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
  - Quantum Mechanics, Teller et al., 1945 -- 1946; MS044.002.001.00013 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
- Class Notes from the University of Illinois, 1942 -- 1950; MS044.003; 2.4 Linear Feet
  This series contains class and lecture notes from Klema's graduate work at the Department of Physics at the University of Illinois, Champaign-Urbana. Courses include Nuclear Physics, Quantum Mechanics, Mechanics and Dynamics, and applied math courses. Notes often consist of the printed course packets by the professors and Klema's handwritten notes for each course. Some folders are only identified by the title "class notes" containing Klema's handwritten notes but do not specify a particular class. While notes from identified classes are clearly from the University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign, it is possible that a few of the unidentified courses are from Klema's later time at Rice University but we were unable to verify this.
  This series is arranged in original order, possibly chronologically.
  - Mechanics and Dynamics (Goldhaber, Klema)(1), 1947; Mechanics and Dynamics from Princeton, 1942; Analytical Dynamics (Bartlett), 1947, 1942 -- 1947; MS044.003.001.00014 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
    possibly contains notes from Klema's time as a student at Princeton, but difficult to determine
  - Mechanics and Dynamics (Goldhaber, Klema)(2), 1947; MS044.003.001.00015 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
  - Bio-Physics (Rabinowitch, Klema), 1948 -- 1949; MS044.003.001.00016 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
  - Class Notes, 1946; MS044.003.001.00017 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
  - Class Notes, 1948; MS044.003.001.00018 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
  - Optics (Almy, Klema), 1946; MS044.003.001.00019 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
  - Quantum Mechanics, 1948 -- 1949; MS044.003.001.00020 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
  - Class Notes, 1950; MS044.003.001.00021 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
    may be from Klema's time at Rice University
  - Kinetic Theory of Gases-Thermodynamics (Rawcliff, Klema), 1947 -- 1948; MS044.003.001.00022 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
  - Problems of Quantum Mechanics, 1948 -- 1950; MS044.003.001.00023 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
  - Class Notes, 1948 -- 1950; MS044.003.001.00024 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
  - Quantum Mechanics (Nordsieck, Klema), 1945 -- 1946; MS044.003.001.00025 (Box MS044 Shared 1)
  - Quantum Mechanics (Nordsieck, Klema), 1948 -- 1949; MS044.003.002.00001 (Box MS044 Shared 2)
  - Electricity - Electro-Magnetism (Nordsieck, Klema), 1947 -- 1948; MS044.003.002.00002 (Box MS044 Shared 2)
  - Quantum Mechanics (Nordsieck, Klema), 1948 -- 1949; MS044.003.002.00003 (Box MS044 Shared 2)
  - Physics 184- Atomic Spectra (Kroger, Klema), 1945 -- 1947; MS044.003.002.00004 (Box MS044 Shared 2)
  - Class Notes, 1949 -- 1950; MS044.003.002.00005 (Box MS044 Shared 2)
  - Nuclear Physics, 1945 -- 1950; MS044.003.002.00006 (Box MS044 Shared 2)
  - Physics 128 (Klema), 1947 -- 1948; MS044.003.002.00007 (Box MS044 Shared 2)
  - Nuclear Physics (Goldhaber), 1946 -- 1947; MS044.003.002.00008 (Box MS044 Shared 2)
  - Class Notes, 1949; MS044.003.002.00009 (Box MS044 Shared 2)
  - Mathematics 175 - Applied Math (Ketchum, Klema), 1946 -- 1947; MS044.003.002.00010 (Box MS044 Shared 2)
  - Mathematics 175 (Ketchum, Klema), 1947 -- 1948; MS044.003.002.00011 (Box MS044 Shared 2)
- Teaching Notes from the Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology, 1950 -- 1958; MS044.004; 2.4 Linear Feet
  This series contains teaching notes from Klema's time at the Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology. Courses include reactor physics lab and nuclear physics. Also included in this series are curriculum files, faculty meeting minutes, and a few research files.
  This series is arranged in original order, which may be chronological.
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Reactor Physics Lab, 1950; MS044.004.002.00012 (Box MS044 Shared 2)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Reactor Physics Lab, 1951; MS044.004.002.00013 (Box MS044 Shared 2)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Reactor Physics Lab, 1951; MS044.004.002.00014 (Box MS044 Shared 2)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Reactor Physics Lab, 1951; MS044.004.002.00015 (Box MS044 Shared 2)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology (1), 1951 -- 1952; MS044.004.002.00016 (Box MS044 Shared 2)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology (2), 1951 -- 1952; MS044.004.002.00017 (Box MS044 Shared 2)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Reactor Physics Lab, 1951 -- 1958; MS044.004.002.00018 (Box MS044 Shared 2)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Nuclear Engineering, 1950 -- 1952; MS044.004.002.00019 (Box MS044 Shared 2)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Curriculum, 1951 -- 1952; MS044.004.002.00020 (Box MS044 Shared 2)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Miscellaneous, 1950 -- 1952; MS044.004.002.00021 (Box MS044 Shared 2)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Curriculum, 1951 -- 1955; MS044.004.003.00001 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Minutes of, 1951 -- 1952; MS044.004.003.00002 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Catalog, 1951 -- 1952; MS044.004.003.00003 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Lecture Notes (1), 1951 -- 1952; MS044.004.003.00004 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Lecture Notes (2), 1951 -- 1952; MS044.004.003.00005 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Laboratory - Reactor, 1951 -- 1952; MS044.004.003.00006 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Lectures, 1951 -- 1957; MS044.004.003.00007 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Miscellaneous, 1950 -- 1952; MS044.004.003.00008 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Laboratory, 1951 -- 1953; MS044.004.003.00009 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - US Atomic Energy Commission [The Role of Engineering in Nuclear Energy Development], 1951; MS044.004.003.00010 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Nuclear Physics Seminar, 1952; MS044.004.003.00011 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Electronic Pile Simulator, 1950; MS044.004.003.00012 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - 4Pi High Pressure Ion Chamber, 1950 -- 1953; MS044.004.003.00013 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Decay of a Radioelement, 1950 -- 1953; MS044.004.003.00014 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Exponential Pile Experiments, 1950 -- 1953; MS044.004.003.00015 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Exponential Pile Flux Distribution, 1951; MS044.004.003.00016 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology - Cooperative Program, 1957; MS044.004.003.00017 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
- Subject files and Publications from Argonne National Laboratory/Association of Midwest Universities/Northwestern University, 1953 -- 1967; MS044.005; 2.4 Linear Feet
  This series contains files when Klema worked as consultant for Argonne National Laboratory/Association of Midwest Universities while professor at Northwestern University. Included are files relating to his contribution to the development of an electron microscope, class notes from the Engineering Practice School at Argonne, research papers from the Practice School (apparently unpublished), and general research files from Argonne. Two oversize drawing from an accelerator project are also included (box 3, folders 19/20). 2 oversize drawings are in Box 4, folder 6 (oversize).
  This series is arranged in original order which is by topic and may be chronological.
  - Engineering Development Studies, 1963; MS044.005.003.00018 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Pert Master Project Schedule - 1000 BEV Alt. Gradient Synchrotron, 1963; MS044.005.003.00019 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Pert Master Project - 1000 BEV Alt. Gradient Synchrotron, 1963; MS044.005.003.00020 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Master Planning Guide - 12.5 BEV FFAG Acelerator, 1963; MS044.005.003.00021 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Argonne Practice School, 1963; MS044.005.003.00022 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Vacuum Characteristics of Gasket Materials, 1963; MS044.005.003.00023 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Master Planning Guide - 12.5 BEV Alt. Grandient Synchrotron, 1963; MS044.005.003.00024 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Evaluation of Two Techniques - Separation of Neptunium-239 from Uranium, 1963; MS044.005.003.00025 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Fabricating Particulate Fuel Rods, 1963; MS044.005.003.00026 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Heat Transfer Study of CP-5 Reactor Fuel Elements, 1963; MS044.005.003.00027 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Analog Determination and Simulation of Triga Feedback Transfer Function, 1963; MS044.005.003.00028 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - High Temperature Physical Properties of Nuclear Ceramic Materials, 1963; MS044.005.003.00029 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Determination of Neutron Flux in UT-53 of CP-5 Reactor, 1963; MS044.005.003.00030 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Fast Reactor Fuel Burnup, 1963; MS044.005.003.00031 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Calculation of Centerline Temperature of Storage Cylinders Filled with Fission Product Wastes from Fluoride Volatility Reprocessing, 1963; MS044.005.003.00032 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Fast Reactor Fuel Burnup, 1963; MS044.005.003.00033 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Vacuum Characteristics of Gasket Materials, 1963; MS044.005.003.00034 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Master Planning Guide - 200 BEV Alt. Grandient Synchrotron, 1963; MS044.005.003.00035 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Associated Midwest Universities - Fact Sheet, 1963; MS044.005.003.00036 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Associated Midwest Universities - Engineering Practice School, 1963; MS044.005.003.00037 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Radiation Losses in Measurement of Thermal Diffusivity, 1963; MS044.005.003.00038 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Wire Orbit Bearing, 1963; MS044.005.003.00039 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Measurement of NaK-78 Vapor Pressure to 25 Atmospheres, 1963; MS044.005.003.00040 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Evaluation of Two Techniques - Separation of Neptunium-239 from Uranium, 1963; MS044.005.003.00041 (Box MS044 Shared 3)
  - Electron Microscope, 1953 -- 1966; MS044.005.004.00001 (Box 4)
  - Electron Microscope, 1967; MS044.005.004.00002 (Box 4)
  - Electron Microscope Meeting, 1964; MS044.005.004.00003 (Box 4)
  - Electron Microscope Meeting, 1965 -- 1966; MS044.005.004.00004 (Box 4)
  - Electron Microscope, 1967; MS044.005.004.00005 (Box 4)
  - Electron Microscope, 1963 -- 1965; MS044.005.004.00006 (Box 4)
  - Field Emission Corporation, 1965 -- 1966; MS044.005.004.00007 (Box 4)
  - Electron Microscope, 1966; MS044.005.004.00008 (Box 4)
  - High Voltage Problems (Klema), 1963 -- 1967; MS044.005.004.00009 (Box 4)
  - High Voltage Electron Microscope Workshop, 1964 -- 1966; MS044.005.004.00010 (Box 4)
  - Electron Microscope, 1961 -- 1966; MS044.005.004.00011 (Box 4)
  - Quadrupole Magnet Aberrations, 1964 -- 1965; MS044.005.004.00012 (Box 4)
  - Argonne National Laboratory (1), 1963 -- 1965; MS044.005.004.00013 (Box 4)
  - Argonne National Laboratory (2), 1963 -- 1965; MS044.005.004.00014 (Box 4)
  - AMU-ANL High Voltage Electron Microscope Workshop (1), 1966; MS044.005.004.00015 (Box 4)
  - AMU-ANL High Voltage Electron Microscope Workshop (2), 1955 -- 1966; MS044.005.004.00016 (Box 4)
  - AMU-ANL High Voltage Electron Microscope Workshop (1), 1964 -- 1966; MS044.005.004.00017 (Box 4)
  - AMU-ANL High Voltage Electron Microscope Workshop (2), 1966 -- 1967; MS044.005.004.00018 (Box 4)
  - AMU (1), 1963 -- 1964; MS044.005.004.00019 (Box 4)
  - AMU (2), 1963; MS044.005.004.00020 (Box 4)
  - Argonne National Laboratory, 1965 -- 1966; MS044.005.004.00021 (Box 4)
  - AMU-ANL High Voltage Electron Microscope Workshop, 1965 -- 1966; MS044.005.004.00022 (Box 4)
  - AMU-ANL High Voltage Electron Microscope Workshop, 1964; MS044.005.004.00023 (Box 4)
  - AMU-ANL High Voltage Electron Microscope Workshop, 1966; MS044.005.004.00024 (Box 4)
  - AMU-ANL High Voltage Electron Microscope Workshop, 1966; MS044.005.004.00025 (Box 4)